<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Art Movements on Artists Are Jerks</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Art Movements on Artists Are Jerks</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/movements/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AI and Algorithmic Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/ai-and-algorithmic-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/ai-and-algorithmic-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AI and Algorithmic Art has existed for many decades, predating popular and widespread availability and usage. Artists in the field work with engineers and computer scientists to code the algorithms, and train the models. Key figures include Refik Anadol, Anna Ridler, and Mario Klingemann. The practice raises conceptual and philosophical questions regarding the nature of art, AI, human/machine interactions, and the future of visual aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Appropriation Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/appropriation-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/appropriation-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Appropriation Art (Readymade?) gained prominence in the 1980s, although its roots can be traced back to earlier movements like Dada and Pop Art. Artists deliberately recontextualize or copy existing images and objects, raising questions about originality, authorship, and the nature of art in a media-saturated culture. Key figures include Sherrie Levine, Richard Prince, and Jeff Koons. Appropriation Art often critiques consumerism, mass media, and the art market itself, prompting viewers to reconsider the meaning and value of cultural artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bio Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/bio-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/bio-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Emerging in the late 20th and early 21st centuries, Bio Art involves working with live bacteria, plants, animals, or human tissues, often in a laboratory setting. It raises ethical questions about the manipulation of life, the relationship between art and science, and the boundaries of the natural world. Key figures include Eduardo Kac, Marta de Menezes, and Stelarc. Bio Art often collaborates with scientists and explores the implications of biotechnology and genetic engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conceptual Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/conceptual-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/conceptual-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conceptual Art emerged in the mid-1960s and emphasizes that the concept or idea behind the artwork is more important than the finished physical object, if one even exists. It can take many forms, including text, documentation, performances, and found objects. Key figures include Sol LeWitt, Joseph Kosuth, and Lawrence Weiner. Conceptual artists often challenge traditional notions of art authorship, skill, and the art market, focusing on the intellectual and theoretical aspects of art-making.TBD&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contemporary Indigenous Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/contemporary-indigenous-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/contemporary-indigenous-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Contemporary Indigenous Art is not a single style, but rather a broad category encompassing the work of artists from Indigenous communities around the world. It often addresses issues of identity, cultural heritage, colonialism, and the environment, while engaging with contemporary art discourses. It can include painting, sculpture, performance, video, and other media. Key figures vary widely by region and cultural background. This art plays a vital role in maintaining and revitalizing Indigenous cultures, while also challenging dominant narratives and promoting cross-cultural understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Art / New Media Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/digital-art-new-media-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/digital-art-new-media-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Emerging with the development of computer technology, Digital Art and New Media Art include a wide range of practices, such as computer graphics, animation, virtual reality, interactive installations, and net art. These works often explore the possibilities and implications of technology, its impact on society, and its relationship to traditional art forms. Key figures include Nam June Paik, Lynn Hershman Leeson, and Olafur Eliasson (who often incorporates digital elements). This field is constantly evolving as new technologies emerge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Installation Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/installation-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/installation-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Installation Art gained prominence in the 1970s, though its origins can be traced back to earlier practices. It involves creating large-scale, mixed-media constructions, often designed for a specific site and intended to be experienced as a total environment. Installation artworks can be temporary or permanent, indoors or outdoors, and often incorporate a variety of materials and sensory experiences. Key figures include Yayoi Kusama, Christo and Jeanne-Claude, and James Turrell. The emphasis is on the viewer&amp;rsquo;s interaction with the artwork and the transformed space.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Land Art / Earthworks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/land-art-earthworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/land-art-earthworks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Emerging in the late 1960s and early 1970s, Land Art involved creating art directly in the landscape, sculpting the land itself or making structures with natural materials like rocks, soil, and water. Often monumental in scale, these works are frequently located in remote areas, subject to natural processes of erosion and decay. Key figures include: Robert Smithson, Walter De Maria, and Nancy Holt. Land Art sought to escape the confines of the gallery and engage with the environment in a direct and powerful way, raising questions about art&amp;rsquo;s relationship to nature, time, and permanence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimalism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/minimalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/minimalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Minimalism emerged in the 1960s as a reaction against the emotionalism of Abstract Expressionism. It emphasized simplicity, objectivity, and the viewer&amp;rsquo;s experience of the artwork in space. Minimalist works often consist of simple geometric forms, repeated units, and industrially produced materials like steel, concrete, and fluorescent lights. Key figures include Donald Judd, Sol LeWitt, and Dan Flavin. The focus is on the physical presence of the object and its relationship to the surrounding environment, rather than any symbolic or emotional meaning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neo-Expressionism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/neo-expressionism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/neo-expressionism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Neo-Expressionism was a reaction against the conceptual and minimalist art of the 1970s. It revived figuration, expressive brushwork, and intense colors, often drawing on historical and mythological themes. Artists sought to convey raw emotion and personal narratives, rejecting the cool detachment of much contemporary art. Key figures include: Julian Schnabel, Georg Baselitz, and Anselm Kiefer. The movement was international in scope and marked a return to more traditional art-making practices, albeit with a postmodern sensibility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/performance-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/performance-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Performance Art emerged as a significant art form in the 1960s, though it has roots in earlier avant-garde movements. It involves live actions presented to an audience, often challenging conventional art forms and incorporating elements of theater, dance, music, and visual art. The artist&amp;rsquo;s body is often the central medium, and the work can be spontaneous or scripted, ephemeral or enduring through documentation. Key figures include Marina Abramović, Chris Burden, and Yoko Ono. Performance art frequently addresses issues of the body, identity, social critique, and the nature of art itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photorealism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/photorealism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/photorealism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Photorealism developed in the late 1960s and early 1970s as a reaction against Abstract Expressionism and Minimalism. Artists meticulously reproduce photographic images on canvas, often using projectors or grids to transfer the image. The subject matter is typically everyday scenes and objects, rendered with a high degree of technical skill and precision. Key figures include: Chuck Close, Richard Estes, and Audrey Flack. Photorealism highlights the relationship between painting and photography, and questions the nature of perception and representation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pop Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/pop-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/pop-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pop Art challenged traditional fine art by incorporating imagery from advertising, comic books, and mundane cultural objects. It often used bold colors, mechanical reproduction techniques like screen printing, and a sense of irony or celebration of consumer culture. Key figures include Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, and Claes Oldenburg. The movement aimed to blur the lines between &amp;ldquo;high&amp;rdquo; art and &amp;ldquo;low&amp;rdquo; culture, reflecting the growing influence of mass media and consumerism on society.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-Internet Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/post-internet-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/post-internet-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Post-Internet Art doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean art made on the internet, but rather art that is deeply influenced by the internet&amp;rsquo;s existence and its effects on culture. It often addresses themes of connectivity, information overload, digital identity, and the blurring of online and offline experiences. It can take many forms, including physical objects, installations, videos, and online platforms. Key figures include: Petra Cortright, Ryan Trecartin, and Hito Steyerl. It acknowledges the internet as a ubiquitous and transformative force in contemporary life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Postminimalism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/postminimalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/postminimalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Postminimalism retains Minimalism&amp;rsquo;s interest in simple forms and industrial materials, but often introduces elements of process, chance, and organic materials. It tends to be more personal and expressive than Minimalism, embracing sensuality, and imperfections. Key figures include: Eva Hesse, Richard Serra, and Bruce Nauman. Postminimalist works often explore the body, the effects of gravity, and the passage of time, emphasizing the physicality of materials and the process of art-making.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relational Aesthetics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/relational-aesthetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/relational-aesthetics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Coined by curator Nicolas Bourriaud in the 1990s, Relational Aesthetics describes art that takes as its starting point the whole of human relations and their social context, rather than an independent and private space. It often involves creating situations or events that encourage interaction and participation among viewers. Key figures include Rirkrit Tiravanija, Liam Gillick, and Philippe Parreno. Relational Aesthetics emphasizes the social function of art and its potential to create new forms of community and dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Practice Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/social-practice-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/social-practice-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social Practice Art emphasizes collaboration, participation, and social engagement as integral aspects of the artwork. It often takes place in the public sphere and addresses social and political issues, aiming to create positive change or raise awareness. Projects can involve workshops, community organizing, interventions, and other forms of direct action. Key figures include: Tania Bruguera, Theaster Gates, and Rick Lowe. The focus is on the process and the impact of the art on individuals and communities, rather than on the creation of a traditional art object.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Street Art / Graffiti Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/street-art-graffiti-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/street-art-graffiti-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Emerging from graffiti subcultures in the 1970s and 1980s, Street Art encompasses a wide range of styles and techniques, including spray paint, stencils, wheatpasting, and murals. It often carries social or political messages, and can be a form of artistic expression, commentary, or protest. Key figures include: Jean-Michel Basquiat, Keith Haring, and Banksy. Street Art challenges traditional notions of art ownership and the gallery system, engaging directly with the public in urban environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Young British Artists (YBAs)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/movements/young-british-artists-ybas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/movements/young-british-artists-ybas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The YBAs gained notoriety in the 1990s for their use of unconventional materials, provocative imagery, and a &amp;ldquo;shock of the new&amp;rdquo; approach. They often explored themes of death, identity, consumerism, and the media, often with a dark sense of humor. Key figures include: Damien Hirst, Tracey Emin, and Sarah Lucas. The YBAs revitalized the British art scene and gained international recognition, but also attracted controversy for their sometimes sensationalist approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
